<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Principles of Artificial Neural Networks and Machine Learning for Bioinformatics Applications</title>
<date>2023-07-26</date>
</info>
<section xml:id="_principles_of_artificial_neural_networks_and_machine_learning_for_bioinformatics_applications">
<title>Principles of Artificial Neural Networks and Machine Learning for Bioinformatics Applications</title>
<simpara>Konstantinos Krampis*<superscript>1</superscript>, Eric Ross<superscript>2</superscript>, Olorunseun O. Ogunwobi<superscript>1</superscript>, Grace Ma,<superscript>3</superscript> Raja Mazumder,<superscript>4</superscript> Claudia Wultsch<superscript>1</superscript></simpara>
<simpara><superscript>1</superscript>Belfer Research Facility, Biological Sciences, Hunter College, City University of New York, NY, USA
<superscript>2</superscript>Fox Chase Cancer Center, Philadephia, PA, USA
<superscript>3</superscript>Center for Asian Health, Lewis Katz School of Medicine, Temple University, Philadelphia, PA, USA
<superscript>4</superscript>Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, George Washington University, Washington D.C., USA</simpara>
<simpara><superscript>*</superscript>Corresponding Author, <emphasis>kk104@hunter.cuny.edu</emphasis></simpara>
<section xml:id="_abstract">
<title>ABSTRACT</title>
<simpara>With the exponential growth of machine learning and development of Artificial
Neural Network (ANNs) in recent years, there is great opportunity to leverage
this approach and accelarate biological discoveries through applications on the
analysis of high-throughput data.  Various types of datasets including for
example protein or gene interaction networks, molecular structures and cellular
signalling pathways, have already been used for machine learning by training
ANNs for inference and pattern classification.  However, unlike regular data
structures that are commonly used in the computer science and engineering
fields, bioinformatics datasets present challenges that require unique
algorithmic approaches.  The recent development of the geometric and deep
learning approach within the machine learning field, is very promising towards
accelerating analysis complex bioinformatics datasets.  The principles of ANNs
and their importance for bioinformatics machine learning is demonstrated
herein, through presentation of the undelying mathematical and statistical
foundations from group theory, symmetry, linear algebra.  Furthermore, the
structure and functions of ANN algorithms that form the core principles of
artificial intelligence are explained, in relation to the bioinformatics data
domain.  Overall, the manuscript provides guidance for researchers to
understand the principles required for practicing machine learning and
artificial intelligence, with the special considerations towards bioinformatics
applications.</simpara>
<simpara>*Keywords:*<emphasis>machine learning, artificial intelligence, bioinformatics, cancer biology, neural networks, symmetry, group theory, algorithms</emphasis></simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_simple_summary">
<title>SIMPLE SUMMARY</title>
<simpara>The present manuscript provides an overview of the formalisms at the foundation
of Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs), that are the basis of Artificial
Intelligence within the broader field of Machine Learning.  The review is from
the perspective of bioinformatics data, and multiple examples of the
applications of the formalisms to experimental scenarios  are presented herein.
The mathematical formalisms are explained in detail, and biologists who are not
Machine Learning experts are provided with the opportunity to understand the
algorithmic basis of Artificial Intelligence towards bioinformatics
applications.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_introduction">
<title>INTRODUCTION</title>
<simpara>In summary, Artificial Intelligence (AI), Machine Learning (ML), and Deep
Learning (DL) are related concepts with key differences: AI focuses on creating
machines that can perform tasks requiring human intelligence, ML enables
computers to learn from data and make predictions without explicit programming,
and DL uses deep neural networks to extract patterns from complex datasets. AI
encompasses ML and DL, which are subsets of AI. ML algorithms learn patterns
from data to make accurate predictions or decisions and can be categorized into
supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning. DL algorithms, inspired
by the human brain, use deep neural networks to learn and extract patterns from
large-scale datasets. DL has had success in image and speech recognition,
natural language processing, and autonomous driving.</simpara>
<simpara>In the last decade, technologies such as genomic sequencing have enabled an
exponential increase [<link linkend="katz2022sequence">1</link>] of the data that describe the
molecular elements, structure and function of biological systems. Furthermore,
data generation in fields as diverse as physics, software development and
social media [<link linkend="clissa2022survey">2</link>], have resulted in datasets of scale not
previously available to scientists. This data abundance, has been fundamental
for the ever accelerating advancements in the field of machine learning, deep
learning and artificial intelligence, where we now  have algorithms that can be
trained to make discoveries from the data, at a level that closely matches
human intuition.</simpara>
<simpara>The field of deep learning and artificial intelligence, has developed rapidly
within the span of a few years, and while researchers have developed hundreds
of successful algorithms, there currently few unifying principles to organize
systematically the machine learning algorithms. In a seminal <literal>proto-book</literal> by
Bronstein et al.  [<link linkend="bronstein2021geometric">3</link>], a range of systematization
principles for the different Artificial Neural Network (ANN) architectures and
deep learning algorithms were presented, based on the concepts of symmetry and
mathematical group theory.  Symmetry and invariance is a central concept in
physics, mathematical and biological systems, and has been established since
the early 20th century that fundamental principles of nature are based on
symmetry [<link linkend="noether1918invariante">4</link>].  The authors also introduced the concept
of geometric deep learning, and demonstrated how the group theory, function
invariance and equivariance principles, can be used as basis towards composing
and describing the various deep learning algorithms. Along these lines, in the
present manuscript we explain the structure of ANNs and the principles of
machine learning algorithms, while providing a review of mathematical and
statistical foundations related to the  development of artificial intelligence
applications with bioinformatics data.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_the_structure_of_artificial_intelligence_and_neural_networks">
<title>THE STRUCTURE OF ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE AND NEURAL NETWORKS</title>
<simpara>We will first describe the structures and function of deep learning and
Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs) that are the basis of artificial intelligence
[<link linkend="li2019deep">5</link>]. Assume a dataset consisting of <emphasis>n</emphasis> pairs of
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>, with the <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> being <emphasis>n</emphasis> data points and <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>
their labels. Each <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> data point can be for example be a number, a
vector (array of numbers), or a matrix (grid of numbers) storing different types
of bioinformatics data.  The labels can be of various formats, such as
binary (two-option) as for example <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inlineequation> "inhibits cancer growth", or
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inlineequation> "does not inhibit cancer". The labels can also be continuous
numbers such as for example <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn></mml:math></inlineequation> meaning 30% inhibition, or a
composite label such as <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> representing respectively drug
attributes such as '0 - no inhibition', '1 - yes for toxicity', '0 - not
metabolized'. Similarly, the input data points can also be composite such as
for example <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> representing two measuments for a single
biological entity. Independently of the label structure, the deep learning
algorithms and the overall goal of artificial intelligence applications for
bioinformatics, is to first train the ANN with data for which the labels are
known, and then perform classification of newly generated data, by predicting
their labels.</simpara>
<simpara>The simplest structure of an artificial neural network as shown on <emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis> is
"fully connected", with each neuron <emphasis>k</emphasis> in the ANN having a number of incoming
and outgoing connections corresponding to the number of neurons in previous and
next layer in the neural network. For example the neuron <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inlineequation> of the
<emphasis>First Layer (1)</emphasis> on <emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis>, has <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inlineequation> incoming and <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inlineequation>
outgoing connections, corresponding respectively to the "input layer" with two
neurons, and three connections with the neurons of the internal ("hidden
layer") labeled <emphasis>Second Layer (2)</emphasis> on the figure. The internal layers are
called "hidden" since they do not receive input data directly, similarly to the
neurons performing cognition in animal brains, as opposed to sensory neurons.
While the hidden layers can have an arbitrary number of neurons based on the
complexity of the label classification problem we need the ANN to resolve
[<link linkend="uzair2020effects">6</link>], the input layer has the exact number of neurons
corresponding to the input data structure. On <emphasis role="strong">Fig. 1</emphasis> for example we have two
input neurons, and the data can be of the form <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation>. Finally,
the output layer has a number of neurons corresponding to the number of labels
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> per input data point in the data, and on <emphasis role="strong">Fig. 1</emphasis> there is a single
label.</simpara>
<informalfigure role="middle">
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Fig1.svg"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Fig1</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>
<simpara><?asciidoc-hr?></simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Figure 1.</emphasis> An example <emphasis role="strong">Artificial Neural Network (ANN)</emphasis>. The signal
aggregation taking place on the second neuron <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> of the
second hidden layer, can be expressed with the formula
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, which is the aggregation of neuron signals from the first
layer, shown as red arrows on the figure. The <emphasis>b</emphasis> is the threshold that needs
to be overcome by the aggregation sum in order for the neuron to fire, and then
the neuron will transmit a signal along the line shown towards the output on
the final layer on the figure. The reader should refer to the text for more
details.</simpara>
<simpara><?asciidoc-hr?></simpara>
<simpara>Similar to neural networks in animal brains, the computational abstractions
used in machine learning and artificial intelligence, model neurons as
computational units performing signal summation and threshold activation.
Specifically, each artificial neuron performs a summation of incoming signals
from its connected neighbooring neurons in the preceeding layer on the network,
shown for example as red arrows on <emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis> for <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>. The
signal processing across the ANN transitions from input data <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> on the
leftmost layer (<emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis>), to output of data labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> on the right end.
Within each neuron, when the aggregated input reaches a certain threshold, the
neuron "fires" and transmits a signal to the next layer. The signals coming
into the neuron can be either the data directly from the input layer, or
signals generated by activation of the neurons in the intermediate - "hidden"
layers. The summation and thresholding computation within each neuron is
represented with the function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, where
the <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> is the connection weights of the preceding neurons. Each
connection arrow on <emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis> has a different weight, such as for example
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> which is the incoming signal from the neuron
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> to neuron <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>, multiplied by the
weight <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>, which represents the strength of the connection between
these two artificial neurons.</simpara>
<simpara>The weights in artificial neural networks represent the strength of connections
between neurons. They determine the impact of input signals on the final output
of the network. During the training process, these weights are adjusted to
minimize the difference between the network&#8217;s predicted output and the desired
output. The weights essentially control the flow of information through the
network, allowing it to learn and make accurate predictions. Correctly tuned
weights are crucial for the network to effectively learn patterns and
generalize its knowledge to new input data.</simpara>
<simpara>For the majority of applications, the weight values <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> are the only
elements in the ANN structure that are variable, and are adjusted by the
algorithms during training with the input data. This is similar to the
biological brain, where learning takes place by strengthening connections among
neurons [<link linkend="wainberg2018deep">7</link>]. However, unlike the biological brain the ANNs
used in practice for data analysis have fixed connections between the neurons
and the structure of the neural network does not change during training and
learning to recognize and classify new data. The last term <emphasis>b</emphasis> in the
summation, represents a threshold that needs to be surpassed such as
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, in order for the neuron to activate.  One
final step before the output value of the neuron is tranmitted, is the
application of a "logit" function to the summation value, that is represented
as <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation>. The <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> can be selected from a range of
non-linear functions depending on the the type of input data, and the specific
analysis and data classification domain for which the ANN will be used
[<link linkend="li2019deep">5</link>]. The value of the logit function is the output of the neuron,
which is transmitted to its connected neurons in the next layer through the
outgoing connections, shown as an arrows on <emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis> and corresponding to the
brain cell axons in the biological analogy. Multiple layers of neurons
connected together in layers (<emphasis role="strong">Fig.1</emphasis>), along with multiple connections per
layer each having each own weight <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>, forms the Artificial Neural
Network (ANN).</simpara>
<simpara>From a mathematical formalism perspective, a trained ANN is a function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>
that predicts labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> such as for example 'no inhibition',
'yes for toxicity' etc., for different types of input data <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> ranging
from histology images to drug molecules represented as graph data structures.
Therefore, the ANN performs data classification as a mapping function
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>, from the input data to the labels. Furthermore, the
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> is a non-linear function, since it is an aggregate composition of
the non-linear functions <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> of the individual
interconnected neurons in the network [<link linkend="li2019deep">5</link>].  As a result, the
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> can classify labels for data inputs that originate from complex
data distributions, and this fact enables ANNs to achieve higher analytical
power compared to typical statistical learning algorithms
[<link linkend="tang2019recent">8</link>]. The <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> is estimated by fitting a training
dataset, which correlates labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> to data points <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>.  With
hundreds of papers and monographs that have been written on the technical
details of training ANNs, we will next attempt to briefly summarize the process
and refer the reader to the citations for further details.</simpara>
<simpara>As mentioned previously, the only variable element in the ANN structure are the
weights <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> of the neuron connections, and therefore training an ANN to
classify data is the estimation of the weights. Furthermore, the training
process involves minimizing the error <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, which is the difference between
the labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> predicted by the function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> and the true
labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>. This error metric is akin to true/false positive and
negatives (precision and recall) used in statistics, however diffent formulas
are used for its estimation for multi-label or complex input data to the ANN
(for more details, [<link linkend="kriegeskorte2019neural">9</link>]). The neuron connection weight
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> estimation by the algorithm takes place by fitting the network
function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> on a large training dataset of <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inlineequation> pairs of
input data and labels, while the error <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> is calculated by using a subset
of the data for testing and validation.  The training algorithm starts with an
initial value of the weights, and then performs multiple cycles (called
"epochs") towards estimating the function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> by fitting the data
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> to the network and calculating the error <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> by comparing
predicted <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> and the true labels <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>. At the end of each
cycle "backpropagation" is performed [<link linkend="tang2019recent">8</link>], which involves a
gradient descent optimization algorithm, in order to fine tune the weights of
the individual neurons and minimize <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>.  The gradient descent
[<link linkend="ruder2016overview">10</link>] searches the possible combinations of weight values,
and since it is a heuristic algorithm it minimizes <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, but cannot reach
zero error. At the completion of multiple training cycles the training
algorithm identifies a set of weights which best fit the data, and the ANN
settles on the optimal values that estimate the <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> function for
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x2211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation>, where <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> is the weight in
each interconnected neuron. Consequently, the overall <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> represented by
the network is also estimated,since as it was mentioned previously is the
composition of the individual <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> neuron functions.  Once
the artificial neural network training has been completed by finding the most
optimal set of weights, it is now ready to be used for label prediction with
new, unknown <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> data.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_artificial_intelligence_group_theory_symmetry_and_invariance">
<title>ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE, GROUP THEORY, SYMMETRY AND INVARIANCE</title>
<simpara>We conclude, by reviewing how the principles of group theory, symmetry and
invariance, provide a foundational framework to understand the function of
machine learning algorithms, and the classifying power of ANNs in relation to
statistical variance, transformations, and non-homogeneity in the input data.
In broad terms, symmetry is the analysis of geometric and algebraic
mathematical structures, and can have applications with data found in the
fields of physics, molecular biology and machine learning. A core concept in
symmetry is invariance, which in our context is changing data coordinates,
such as shifting a drug molecule in space or a cancer histology tissue sample,
while leaving the shape of the object unchanged [<link linkend="bronstein2021geometric">3</link>].
Following such a change which as will be formally defined later in the text as
<emphasis>invariant transformation</emphasis>, the machine learning algorithms and ANNs must be able
to recognize a drug molecule following rotation, or a tissue to be recognized
as cancerous from a shifted histology image.</simpara>
<simpara>In order to link the abstract symmetry concepts with data classification in
machine learning, following the terminology of Bronstein et al., we consider
the input data <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> to originate from a symmetry domain <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation>. The
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation> is the structure upon which the data are based, and upon the
domain structure we train the artificial neural networks to perform
classification, through the label prediction function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inlineequation> as mentioned in
the earlier section. For example, microscopy images are essentially
2-dimensional numerical grids of <emphasis>n x n</emphasis> pixels (<emphasis role="strong">Fig.2a</emphasis>), with each pixel
having a value for the light intensity captured when the image was taken. In
this case the data domain is a grid of integers (<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation>), represented as
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#xD7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>. Similarly, for color images the data domain is
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2192;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#xD7;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inlineequation>, with three overlayed integer grids each
representing the green, blue and red layers composing the color image. In
either case, the <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation> contains all possible combinations of pixel
intensities, while the specific pixel value combinations of the images in the
input data <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation>  are a "signal" <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> from the domain.  The
ANN data classification and label prediction function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation>
is applied on the signal <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> which is essentially a subset of
the domain <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation>.</simpara>
<simpara>A <emphasis>symmetry group</emphasis> <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> contains all possible transformations of the
input signal <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> called symmetries <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> or
otherwise <emphasis>group actions</emphasis>. A symmetry transformation <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> preserves
the properties of the data, such as for example not distorting the objects in
the image during rotation. The members of the symmetry group <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g \in
G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g \in
G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> are the associations of two or more coordinate points <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[u,v\in \Omega]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[u,v\in \Omega]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>
on the data domain (grid in our image example). Between these coordinates, the image can be rotated,
shifted or otherwise transformed without any distortion. Therefore, the key aspect
of the formal mathematical definition of the group, is that the data attributes
are preserved during object distortions that are common during the experimental
acquisition of bioinformatics data. The concept of symmetry groups is
important towards modeling the performance of machine learning algorithms, for
classifying the data patterns correctly, despite the variability found in the input data.</simpara>
<informalfigure role="left">
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Fig2a.svg"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Fig2a</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>
<informalfigure role="right">
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="Fig2b.svg"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Fig2b</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</informalfigure>
<simpara><?asciidoc-hr?></simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Figure 2. (a).</emphasis> A <emphasis>grid</emphasis> data structure representing image pixels, and
formally is a <emphasis>graph</emphasis> <emphasis role="strong">(b).</emphasis> A <emphasis>graph</emphasis> <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[G = (V, E)]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[G = (V, E)]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>, is composed of
<emphasis>nodes</emphasis> <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[V]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[V]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> shown as circles, and <emphasis>edges</emphasis>  connecting the nodes and
shown as arrows. It can represent a protein, where the amino acids are the
nodes and the peptide bonds between amino acids are the edges.</simpara>
<simpara><?asciidoc-hr?></simpara>
<simpara>Another important data structure for bioinformatics is a <emphasis>graph</emphasis> <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[G
= (V, E)]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[G
= (V, E)]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>, composed of <emphasis>nodes</emphasis> <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[V]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[V]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> representing biological
entities, and <emphasis>edges</emphasis>  which are the connections between pairs of nodes
(<emphasis role="strong">Fig.2b</emphasis>).  In a specific instance of a graph for a real-world object,  the
edges are a subset of all possible links between nodes. An example graph data
structure for a biological molecule such a protein or a drug, would represent
the amino acids or atoms as node entities, and the chemical bonds between each
of these entities as edges. The edges can correspond to either the
carbonyl-amino (C-N) peptide bonds between amino acids and molecular
interactions across the peptide chain on the protein structure, or the chemical
bonds between atoms in a drug molecule. Furthermore, attributes in the
molecular data such as for example polarity and amino acid weight, or drug
binding properties can be represented as <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[s]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[s]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> - dimensional node
attributes, where <emphasis>s</emphasis> are the attributes assigned to each node.  Similarly, the
edges or even entire graphs can have attributes, for experimental data measured
on the molecular interactions represented by the edges, and measurements of the
properties of the complete protein or drug.  Finally, from an algorithmic
perspective , images are a special case of graphs where the nodes are the
pixels, and connect with edges in a structured pattern that form of a grid
(<emphasis role="strong">Fig.2a</emphasis>) representing the adjacent position of the pixels.</simpara>
<simpara>Having established the mathematical and algorithmic parallels between graphs
and images, we will now utilize the principles of the <emphasis>symmetry group</emphasis>
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> to examine the analytical and classification power of machine
learning ANNs, in relation to variability and transformations in the data. For
both data types such as input images or molecules represented as graphs that
are shifted or rotated, we establish the concept of invariance through the
principles of group theory and symmetry. These are the foundational
mathematical and algorithmic formalisms, that can be used to model the
performance and output of machine learning algorithms ANNs in relation to the
variability in the dataset. Consecutively, these principles can then be
extrapolated and generalized for other types of data beyond graphs and images,
for which ANNs are trained for prediction and classification. While we present
the group and symmetry definitions following a data-centric approach, we will
nonetheless still follow the mathematical formalism, when describing how the
group operations can transform the input data. Furtermore, different types of
data can have the same symmetry group, and different transformations can be
performed by the same group operation. For example, an image with a triangle
which essentially is a graph with three nodes, can have the same rotational
symmetry group as a graph of three nodes or a numerical sequence of three
elements.</simpara>
<simpara>When chemical and biological molecules are represented as graphs as described
earlier, the nodes <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[V]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[V]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> can be in any order depending on how the
data were measured during the experiment.   This does not change the meaning of
the data, and as long as the edges <emphasis role="strong">E</emphasis> representing the connections between
the molecules are not modified, we have a proper representation of the
molecular entity independently of the ordering of <emphasis role="strong">V</emphasis>. In this case, where
two graphs for the same molecule have the same edges but different ordering of
nodes, they are called <emphasis>isomorphic</emphasis>. Any machine learning algorithm performing
pattern recognition on graphs, should not depend on the ordering of nodes so
that classification with ANNs and artificial intelligence is not affected by
experiment measurement variations in real-world data.  This is something that
is taken for granted with human intelligence, where for example we can
recognize an object even when a photograph is rotated at an angle. Returning to
our formal definitions, in order for ANNs algorithms to equivalently recognize
<emphasis>isomorphic</emphasis> graphs, the functions <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>&#x3C6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x3C3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> and overall
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> of the ANN acting on graph data should be <emphasis>permutation
invariant</emphasis>.This means that for any permutation of the input dataset, the output
value of these functions are identical independently of the ordering of the
nodes <emphasis role="strong">V</emphasis> for example in the case of graphs. This concept can be similarly
applied to images, which as mentioned previously are special cases of fully
connected graphs, and furthermore these principles can also be generalized to
other data types beyond images or graphs.</simpara>
<simpara>In order to formalize further the concept of invariance, and since both
examples of the image and graphs are similarly points on a grids on a two
dimemensional plane, we can use linear algebra. Specifically, by using a matrix
we can represent the data transformations as group actions <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>,
within the symmetry group <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>. The use of matrices enables us to
connect the group symmetries with the actual data, through matrix
multiplications that modify the coordinates of the object and consecutively
represent the data transformations through the multiplication. The dimensions
of the matrix <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[n \times n]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[n \times n]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> are usually similar to these of the
signal space <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> for the data (for example, <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#xD7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x2124;</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> images).
The the matrix dimensions not depend on the size of the group i.e.  the number
of possible symmetries, or the dimensionality of underlying data domain
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\Omega]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\Omega]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>. With this definition in place, we can formalize
symmetries and group actions for modifying data objects, and the use of matrix
and linear transformations as basis for connecting invariance in relation to
variability in the data.</simpara>
<simpara>We will now conclude by establishing the mathematical and linear algebra
formalisms, for resilience of the ANNs and machine learning algorithm pattern
recognition, in relation to transformations in the data. While our framework is
on a two-dimensional, grid data domain <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\Omega]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\Omega]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>, the formalisms
developed here can also be extrapolated without loss of generality to any
number of dimensions or data formats. We will first connect matrices to group
actions <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> (rotations, shifts etc.) in the symmetry group
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g \in G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g \in G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>, by defining a function <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\theta]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\theta]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> that maps
the group to a matrix as <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\theta : G \rightarrow \mathbf{M}]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\theta : G \rightarrow \mathbf{M}]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>. As
mentioned previously, a matrix  <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\mathbf{M} \in  R^{n \times n}]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\mathbf{M} \in  R^{n \times n}]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> of
numerical values (integers, fractions, positive and negative), when multiplied
to the coordinate values of an object on the plane <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\Omega]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\Omega]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>, it
rotates or shifts the object coordinates for the exact amount correponsing to
the group action within the symmetry group.</simpara>
<simpara>With these definitions in place, we will now connect the matrix formalisms with
the neural network estimator function <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation>, that is
identified by adjusting neuron connection weights during multiple training
cycles with the input data.  Our goal is to leverage the mathematical
formalisms of group symmetry and invariance, in order to establish the ANN
resilience for classifying and assigning labels to new data points. The data
points originate from real-world data that might contain tranformations and
distortions. We first define that the estimator function of the ANN to be
<emphasis>invariant</emphasis>, if the condition for the input data holds such as
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[f(\mathbf{M} \times x_i) = f(x_i)]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[f(\mathbf{M} \times x_i) = f(x_i)]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> for all matrices
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\mathbf{M}]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\mathbf{M}]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> representing the actions <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[g \in G]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[g \in G]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> within
the symmetry group. This formula presents the condition required for the neural
network function to be invariant: its output value is the same whether the
input data <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> are transformed or not (i.e an image or graph is not
rotated on the plane), as this is represented by the matrix multiplication
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\mathbf{M} \times x_i]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\mathbf{M} \times x_i]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> . Therefore, the output values
<inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inlineequation> by the ANN which are essentially predicted output
labels (i.e <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inlineequation> = potent drug / not potent etc.) based on the
input data, are resilient to noisy and deformed real-world data, when the
network estimator function is invariant.  In a different case, the estimator
function approximated by the ANN can be <emphasis>equivariant</emphasis> and defined as
<inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[f(\mathbf{M} \times x_i) = \mathbf{M} \times f(x_i)]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[f(\mathbf{M} \times x_i) = \mathbf{M} \times f(x_i)]]></mathphrase></inlineequation>. This means
that the output of the ANN will be modified, but the label prediction result
will be equally shifted along with the shift in the input data.</simpara>
<simpara>Up to this point, we have discussed only discrete tranformations in linear
algebra terms, with matrix multiplications that result in a shift of
coordinates and rigid transformations of the data, such as a rotation of the
image or the graph by a specific angle on the grid <inlineequation><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mo>&#x3A9;</mml:mo></mml:math></inlineequation>. However, we
can have also also have continuous, more fine grained shifts which is common
with real-world data. In this case, the ANNs algorithms should be able to
recognize patterns, classify and label the data without any loss of
performance. Mathematically, the continuous transformations follow equally with
the invariant and equivariant functions described earlier.  If for example the
domain <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\Omega]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\Omega]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> contains data that have smooth transformations and
shifts, such as moving images (video) or shifts of molecules and graphs that
preserve <emphasis>continuity</emphasis> in a topological definition
[<link linkend="sutherland2009introduction">11</link>], in this case we have a <emphasis>homeomorphism</emphasis>
instead of <emphasis>invariance</emphasis>.</simpara>
<simpara>Finally, if the rate of continuous transformation of the data is quantifiable,
meaning that the function <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\theta]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\theta]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> that maps the group to a matrix
is <emphasis>differentiable</emphasis>, then the members of the symmetry groups will be part of a
<emphasis>diffeomorphism</emphasis>. As it follows from the principles of calculus, in this case
infinitely multiple matrices <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[f(\mathbf(M)]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[f(\mathbf(M)]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> will be needed to be
produced by <inlineequation><alt><![CDATA[\theta]]></alt><mathphrase><![CDATA[\theta]]></mathphrase></inlineequation> for the continuous change of the data
coordinates at every point. These differentiable data structures are common
with manifolds, which for example could be used to represent proteins in fine
detail. In this case the molecule would be represented as cloud with all atomic
forces around the structure, instead of the discrete data structure of nodes
and edges of a graph.  Finally, if the manifold structure includes also a
metric of <emphasis>distance</emphasis> between its points to further quantify the data
transformations, in this case we will have an <emphasis>isometry</emphasis> during the
transformation due to a group action from the symmetry group.</simpara>
</section>
<section xml:id="_applications_of_ai_in_bioinformatics">
<title>APPLICATIONS OF AI IN BIOINFORMATICS</title>
<simpara>Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Deep Learning have emerged as a powerful tool
with diverse applications in the field of bioinformatics, and multiple research
studies have been reported in the literature
[<link linkend="pmid37446831">12</link>, <link linkend="pmid37189058">13</link>, <link linkend="pmid37043378">14</link>], which showcase the potential of
the technology to revolutionize healthcare and life sciences.  One of the
significant applications is drug discovery, as AI algorithms enable the
analysis of large datasets of chemical compounds, predicting their
effectiveness and safety [<link linkend="pmid37479540">15</link>, <link linkend="pmid37458097">16</link>, <link linkend="pmid37454742">17</link>]. These
studies have ddemonstrated that AI can accelerate the drug discovery process by
screening potential candidates and optimizing their properties, leading to
significant cost and time savings.</simpara>
<simpara>In the field of genomics AI algorithms have been applied to the analysis of DNA
sequencing and gene expression data, facilitating the identification of
disease-causing mutations and understanding genetic variations
[<link linkend="pmid37453366">18</link>, <link linkend="pmid37446311">19</link>, <link linkend="pmid37386009">20</link>, <link linkend="pmid37370847">21</link>]. Furthermore, in
these studies, genomic data analysis with AI algorithms has resulted into
insights which can aid towards the development of personalized medicine
approaches and as result to tailor treatments to individual patients.
Consecutively, use of AI algorithms for bioinformatics can contribute towards
development of precision medicine.  By integratively analyzing patient data,
including genetic information, medical history, and lifestyle factors, with the
help of AI insight we can better predict drug responses, identify potential
side effects, and suggest optimal treatment options for individual patients.</simpara>
<simpara>This personalized medicine approach can also involve enhancing patient care and
treatment outcomes, through disease diagnosis enhanced by machine learning
analysis of medical images, including MRI scans, X-rays, and histopathology
images, of diseases like cancer
[<link linkend="pmid37488621">22</link>, <link linkend="pmid37478073">23</link>, <link linkend="pmid37474003">24</link>, <link linkend="pmid37449611">25</link>]. The AI algorithms
can assist pathologists and radiologists in making accurate diagnoses, for
early detection and diagnosis and to overall improve patient outcomes.</simpara>
<simpara>AI can also play a significant role in aiding the development of bioinformatics
tools and software through acceleration of code delopment for the analysis and
interpretation of biological data, such as sequence alignment, protein
structure prediction, and functional annotation
[<link linkend="pmid37329982">26</link>, <link linkend="pmid37463768">27</link>, <link linkend="pmid37460991">28</link>].  Moreover, AI-powered natural
language processing techniques have been used to analyze scientific literature,
patents, and clinical trial reports. This enables researchers to stay updated
with the latest discoveries and facilitates knowledge discovery in the field.</simpara>
<simpara>Finally, in the area of clinical trials machine learning algorithms have been
appplied to mining vast amounts of data from clinical trials , and as result
improving the rates of success for new drugs and treatment strategies for
patients partipating in the trials [<link linkend="pmid37486997">29</link>, <link linkend="pmid37483175">30</link>]. Additional
studies have also demonstated that machine learning algorithms can result in
better optimization of the clinical trial designs, reduction costs and overall
acceleration of the drug development pipelines
[<link linkend="pmid37479540">15</link>, <link linkend="pmid37458097">16</link>].</simpara>
<section xml:id="_conclusion">
<title>CONCLUSION</title>
<simpara>The accelerated developments in the fields of Machine Learning and Artificial
Intelligence in recent years, have also had significant impact in the field of
Bioinformatics. Due to the rapid developements, there has been diminished
opportunity to categorize the algorithms and their applications, along with
their perfomance with different types of bioinformatics data.  By leveraging
the symmetry and group theory mathematical formalisms, we can establish the
priciples of operation of Artificial Intelligence algorithms with
bioinformatics data and the directions for future development in the field.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Funding Information:</emphasis> This work has been supported by Award Number U54
CA221704(5) From The National Cancer Institute.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Author Contributions:</emphasis> K.Krampis wrote the manuscript and performed the
research. C. Wultch provided overview during the development of the rresearch
and the manuscrit. E.Ross, O.Ogunwobi, G. Ma and R. Mazumder contributed to the
development of the research and provided feedback during the development of the
manuscript.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Conflict of Interest:</emphasis> The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Institutional Review Board Statement:</emphasis> Not Applicable.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Informed Consent Statement:</emphasis> Not Applicable.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Data Availability Statement:</emphasis> No data were generated as part of the present
review paper.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Acknowledgments:</emphasis> The authors would like to thank their respective
institutions for supporting their scholarly work.</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">Conflicts of Interest:</emphasis> The authors declare no conflict of interest.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="katz2022sequence" xreflabel="[katz2022sequence]"/>[1] K. Katz, O. Shutov, R. Lapoint, M. Kimelman, J. R. Brister, and C. OSullivan, The sequence read archive: a decade more of explosive growth, <emphasis>Nucleic acids research</emphasis>, vol. 50, no. D1, pp. D387D390, 2022.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="clissa2022survey" xreflabel="[clissa2022survey]"/>[2] L. Clissa, Survey of Big Data sizes in 2021. 2022.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="bronstein2021geometric" xreflabel="[bronstein2021geometric]"/>[3] M. M. Bronstein, J. Bruna, T. Cohen, and P. Velikovi, Geometric deep learning: Grids, groups, graphs, geodesics, and gauges, <emphasis>arXiv preprint arXiv:2104.13478</emphasis>, 2021.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="noether1918invariante" xreflabel="[noether1918invariante]"/>[4] E. Noether, Invariante variationsprobleme, math-phys, <emphasis>Klasse, pp235-257</emphasis>, 1918.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="li2019deep" xreflabel="[li2019deep]"/>[5] Y. Li, C. Huang, L. Ding, Z. Li, Y. Pan, and X. Gao, Deep learning in bioinformatics: Introduction, application, and perspective in the big data era, <emphasis>Methods</emphasis>, vol. 166, pp. 421, 2019.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="uzair2020effects" xreflabel="[uzair2020effects]"/>[6] M. Uzair and N. Jamil, Effects of hidden layers on the efficiency of neural networks, in <emphasis>2020 IEEE 23rd international multitopic conference (INMIC)</emphasis>, 2020, pp. 16.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="wainberg2018deep" xreflabel="[wainberg2018deep]"/>[7] M. Wainberg, D. Merico, A. Delong, and B. J. Frey, Deep learning in biomedicine, <emphasis>Nature biotechnology</emphasis>, vol. 36, no. 9, pp. 829838, 2018.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="tang2019recent" xreflabel="[tang2019recent]"/>[8] B. Tang, Z. Pan, K. Yin, and A. Khateeb, Recent advances of deep learning in bioinformatics and computational biology, <emphasis>Frontiers in genetics</emphasis>, vol. 10, p. 214, 2019.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="kriegeskorte2019neural" xreflabel="[kriegeskorte2019neural]"/>[9] N. Kriegeskorte and T. Golan, Neural network models and deep learning, <emphasis>Current Biology</emphasis>, vol. 29, no. 7, pp. R231R236, 2019.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="ruder2016overview" xreflabel="[ruder2016overview]"/>[10] S. Ruder, An overview of gradient descent optimization algorithms, <emphasis>arXiv preprint arXiv:1609.04747</emphasis>, 2016.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="sutherland2009introduction" xreflabel="[sutherland2009introduction]"/>[11] W. A. Sutherland, <emphasis>Introduction to metric and topological spaces</emphasis>. Oxford University Press, 2009.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37446831" xreflabel="[pmid37446831]"/>[12] M. Lee, Recent Advances in Deep Learning for Protein-Protein Interaction Analysis: A Comprehensive Review, <emphasis>Molecules</emphasis>, vol. 28, no. 13, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37189058" xreflabel="[pmid37189058]"/>[13] M. Wysocka, O. Wysocki, M. Zufferey, D. Landers, and A. Freitas, A systematic review of biologically-informed deep learning models for cancer: fundamental trends for encoding and interpreting oncology data, <emphasis>BMC Bioinformatics</emphasis>, vol. 24, no. 1, p. 198, May 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37043378" xreflabel="[pmid37043378]"/>[14] B. Jahanyar, H. Tabatabaee, and A. Rowhanimanesh, Harnessing Deep Learning for Omics in an Era of COVID-19, <emphasis>OMICS</emphasis>, vol. 27, no. 4, pp. 141152, Apr. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37479540" xreflabel="[pmid37479540]"/>[15] F. W. Pun, I. V. Ozerov, and A. Zhavoronkov, AI-powered therapeutic target discovery, <emphasis>Trends Pharmacol Sci</emphasis>, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37458097" xreflabel="[pmid37458097]"/>[16] G. Floresta, C. Zagni, V. Patamia, and A. Rescifina, How can artificial intelligence be utilized for de novo drug design against COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2)?, <emphasis>Expert Opin Drug Discov</emphasis>, pp. 14, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37454742" xreflabel="[pmid37454742]"/>[17] Y. Zhou <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Deep learning in preclinical antibody drug discovery and development, <emphasis>Methods</emphasis>, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37453366" xreflabel="[pmid37453366]"/>[18] A. rez-Mena, E. n, M. J. Alvarez-Cubero, A. Anguita-Ruiz, L. J. Martinez-Gonzalez, and J. Alcala-Fdez, Explainable artificial intelligence to predict and identify prostate cancer tissue by gene expression, <emphasis>Comput Methods Programs Biomed</emphasis>, vol. 240, p. 107719, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37446311" xreflabel="[pmid37446311]"/>[19] W. Wei, Y. Li, and T. Huang, Using Machine Learning Methods to Study Colorectal Cancer Tumor Micro-Environment and Its Biomarkers, <emphasis>Int J Mol Sci</emphasis>, vol. 24, no. 13, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37386009" xreflabel="[pmid37386009]"/>[20] D. Shigemizu <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Classification and deep-learning-based prediction of Alzheimer disease subtypes by using genomic data, <emphasis>Transl Psychiatry</emphasis>, vol. 13, no. 1, p. 232, Jun. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37370847" xreflabel="[pmid37370847]"/>[21] Z. Mirza <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Identification of Novel Diagnostic and Prognostic Gene Signature Biomarkers for Breast Cancer Using Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning Assisted Transcriptomics Analysis, <emphasis>Cancers (Basel)</emphasis>, vol. 15, no. 12, Jun. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37488621" xreflabel="[pmid37488621]"/>[22] R. Adam, K. DellAquila, L. Hodges, T. Maldjian, and T. Q. Duong, Deep learning applications to breast cancer detection by magnetic resonance imaging: a literature review, <emphasis>Breast Cancer Res</emphasis>, vol. 25, no. 1, p. 87, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37478073" xreflabel="[pmid37478073]"/>[23] Y. Tong <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Prediction of lymphoma response to CAR T cells by deep learning-based image analysis, <emphasis>PLoS One</emphasis>, vol. 18, no. 7, p. e0282573, 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37474003" xreflabel="[pmid37474003]"/>[24] L. R. Archila <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Performance of an Artificial Intelligence Model for Recognition and Quantitation of Histologic Features of Eosinophilic Esophagitis on Biopsy Samples, <emphasis>Mod Pathol</emphasis>, p. 100285, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37449611" xreflabel="[pmid37449611]"/>[25] Q. Li, A. Sandoval, and B. Chen, Advancing spinal cord injury research with optical clearing, light sheet microscopy, and artificial intelligence-based image analysis, <emphasis>Neural Regen Res</emphasis>, vol. 18, no. 12, pp. 26612662, Dec. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37329982" xreflabel="[pmid37329982]"/>[26] M. Santorsola and F. Lescai, The promise of explainable deep learning for omics data analysis: Adding new discovery tools to AI, <emphasis>N Biotechnol</emphasis>, vol. 77, pp. 111, Jun. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37463768" xreflabel="[pmid37463768]"/>[27] B. Waissengrin <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Artificial intelligence (AI) molecular analysis tool assists in rapid treatment decision in lung cancer: a case report, <emphasis>J Clin Pathol</emphasis>, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37460991" xreflabel="[pmid37460991]"/>[28] F. Hosseini, F. Asadi, H. Emami, and M. Ebnali, Machine learning applications for early detection of esophageal cancer: a systematic review, <emphasis>BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</emphasis>, vol. 23, no. 1, p. 124, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37486997" xreflabel="[pmid37486997]"/>[29] S. M. Ahmed, R. V. Shivnaraine, and J. C. Wu, FDA Modernization Act 2.0 Paves the Way to Computational Biology and Clinical Trials in a Dish, <emphasis>Circulation</emphasis>, vol. 148, no. 4, pp. 309311, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
<simpara><anchor xml:id="pmid37483175" xreflabel="[pmid37483175]"/>[30] A. Aliper <emphasis>et al.</emphasis>, Prediction of clinical trials outcomes based on target choice and clinical trial design with multi-modal artificial intelligence, <emphasis>Clin Pharmacol Ther</emphasis>, Jul. 2023.</simpara>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</article>